So in this video we are going to be discussing about server manager and how to use server
manager to manage our disk and also the disk cleanup.
So what is server manager?
server manager is actually a management consulting windows server that helps IT professionals
provision a managed protocol and remove windows based servers from their desktops.
Without actually you requiring it are physical assets to the servers or the need to enable
remove desktop protocol that there are the big connections to each server.
So we can use server manager to for example to examine, examine volumes and disk format delete
extend our driver letters and also set up storage and pause.
So if I click file and storage service here you can see we have for example have our
server so all of the servers that we added to this server will be listed here and you
guess it will have our volumes that all the volumes on this device and then we have our
disk at a different disk and if you've created a storage pool definitely you're going
to see your storage pool available here.
And also what you want to also do is for example you come from the server manager who
would do it disk cleanup.
So disk cleanup is a maintenance utility that was developed by Microsoft for its windows
operating system.
So you have it in Windows server, Windows 10, Windows 11, Windows 8 and Windows 7.
So this comes your computer hard drive for files that you no longer need such as temporary
files, cache to web pages and rejected items that ends up in your system recycle bin.
So if for example if I go to my if I go to choose here you can see we have this clean
up.
So by clicking this clean up it's going to open this clean up which this is trying to calculate
how much space I have left that can actually clean up.
So let us wait for this to open onto my here you can see I will go.
So now you can see we have more options or files we can actually delete it.
For example I'll be using this device for a very long time probably you have some files to
be deleted from the disk cleanup and also we can also go to more options and here we can
actually click on the programs and features to remove programs we don't actually need
any more from this device.
And from the disk cleanup also for example if I say let's say I want to actually delete
the following after selecting all the files you want to delete for example the Microsoft
defensive errors and I can we just say okay and it's going to ask you if I show you
want to permanently delete this files I would say delete files and files will be deleted.
And also and also from the server manager we can't really go to choose from tools you
can see we have the open to a little defragment and optimize drive drive.
So this customization process constantly dates the free space on your hard disk by removing
unwanted items before optimizing can help create a larger area of empty space.
So you can see that this moment says zero fragmented and we can do this after the file
we can set to analyze and check if there are any files we need to actually fragment
we can see the temperature is fragmented and now we cannot see we want to automatically
optimize to see it's going to analyze and before it's now start defragmenting our disk.
So this I want a few things about what you are going to do with a server manager both
in regards to disk management.